<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Concerning the church: or, of the church-state under the Gospel Whereby it may appear what a miserable apostacy from the truth hath overspread and covered the earth for many ages and generations, and how gross and thick the darkness yet lies upon it, though the light of God in his tender mercy hath broke forth and shined upon the people of his gathering, and through them hath also visited the world. The guidance of this in my heart, was particularly and chiefly towards the Papists, but I afterwards had a true sence, that it also extended to the state of such Protestants, as had not waited on the Lord, ... Written in Alisbury prison about the middle of the 6th month, 1666. By Issac Penington. Whereunto is annexed, Some observations upon the eternal judgment, as it is expressed by Christ, Mat.25.31 to the end of the chapter.</title>
            <author>Penington, Isaac, 1616-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1666</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224045</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834660</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834660</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39164</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54027)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39164)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1818:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Concerning the church: or, of the church-state under the Gospel Whereby it may appear what a miserable apostacy from the truth hath overspread and covered the earth for many ages and generations, and how gross and thick the darkness yet lies upon it, though the light of God in his tender mercy hath broke forth and shined upon the people of his gathering, and through them hath also visited the world. The guidance of this in my heart, was particularly and chiefly towards the Papists, but I afterwards had a true sence, that it also extended to the state of such Protestants, as had not waited on the Lord, ... Written in Alisbury prison about the middle of the 6th month, 1666. By Issac Penington. Whereunto is annexed, Some observations upon the eternal judgment, as it is expressed by Christ, Mat.25.31 to the end of the chapter.</title>
                  <author>Penington, Isaac, 1616-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 5-20   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.]</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London,</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year, 1666.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Some observations upon the eternal judgment," has a caption title p.16..</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39164:1"/>
            <p>CONCERNING THE CHURCH: OR, Of the Church-State Under the GOSPEL.</p>
            <p>Whereby it may appear what a miſerable Apoſtacy from the Truth hath overſpread and covered the Earth for many Ages and Generations, and how groſs and thick the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs yet lies upon it, though the Light of God in his tender Mercy hath broke forth and ſhined upon the People of his gathering, and through them hath alſo viſited the World.</p>
            <p>The guidance of this in my heart, was particularly and chiefly towards the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> but I afterwards had a true ſence, that it alſo extended to the ſtate of ſuch <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as had not waited on the Lord, for him (in his Wiſdom and Power) to rear up his own Building, but had ventured to build of themſelves, and ſo had reared up Churches in the ſame ſpirit of Error, Darkneſs, and Apoſtacy, which they ſeemed to depart from: againſt all which the Lord will fight, and all which he will break down, in the day of the revelation of the glorious Light and Power of his Truth, which will overcome, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due and reign over the Earth, not after the manner of men, but in the heavenly dominion of his Life.</p>
            <p>Written in <hi>Alisbury</hi> Priſon about the middle of the 6th Month, 1666.</p>
            <p>By ISAAC PENINGTON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is annexed,</hi> Some Obſervations upon the Eternal Judgment, as it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31. to the end of the chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1666.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:39164:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39164:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe the corruption of the Chriſtian Doctrine and Worſhip hath been great (yea indeed very great) ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles; and the Judgements alſo are to be very great, becauſe of this Corruption, even dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Woes, Plagues, Cups of Wrath and Thunders unutterable, as is expreſſed in the Book of the <hi>Revelations.</hi> Therefore, that men may avoid the terrible Wrath of God, which is brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and to break forth, by diſcerning and forſaking that, which his Wrath is againſt; therefore, I ſay, in tender bowels was it in my heart to diſcover ſomewhat of that, which the Lord hath made manifeſt to me (among many others) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the creeping in of this corrupt ſtate, and its getting up after the dayes of the Apoſtles, with its continuance to this day; that Men and Churches may conſider their ſtate, ſee their nakedneſs, and look after the pure Garment, that they may be cloathed with the Spirit of the Lord, and found in the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs thereof, that ſo they may ſtand boldly before him, when the tranſgreſſors and hypocrites (of all ſorts) ſhall have their fig-leaf coverings ripped off, and lie open to the ſtrokes of his Indignation. And this I ſay to all; Take heed of two things, in this Day of the LORD'S Love and Vengeance; Take heed of retaining or ſetting up any thing, which the Lord is coming forth againſt; and take heed of ſlighting or appearing againſt that, which the Lord is preparing to ſet up. The appearance of his Spirit, the ſhining of his Day is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, even in the meaneſt glimmerings of it. O who ſhall be guiltleſs before him, who defendeth or ſetteth up any thing of man's will or wiſdom (his Sun, Moon and Stars, in all their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, being to fall and loſe their ſhining) or who debaſeth the loweſt appearance of his Seed! And if the <hi>Jews</hi> ſuffered ſo deeply, for refuſing and deſpiſing Chriſt's appearance in fleſh,
<pb facs="tcp:39164:3"/>
what will light on thoſe who refuſe and deſpiſe his appearance in Spirit? I know this, that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> now over-look and ſlight this, as the <hi>Jews</hi> did that, and by the ſame ſnare, even by a prejudice they have drunk in, that this is contrary to the Scriptures, as the <hi>Jews</hi> then did conclude, that that coming of Chriſt then was not agreeable to, but different from what the Scriptures had ſaid concerning his coming. But what ſaid Chriſt then? <hi>Wiſdom is juſtified of her Children.</hi> They, who then were of the Spirit, and in the Spirit, knew the voice of the Bridegroom then. And ſuch alſo know it now, and rejoyce in it; though the wiſe in another wiſdom (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures, as they think) refuſe and diſdain it; and not knowing the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt in Spirit, ſet up a Righteouſneſs of their own in fleſh: for their belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (and applying to themſelves the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt) out of the true limits of Life, according to their own appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of things, is no other. And this muſt fall. Man's knowledge of Scriptures, the faith of man, through his own apprehenſions, muſt fall; and man appear naked underneath; that the glorious Righteouſneſs of Chriſt in Spirit, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious covering thereof may be magnified over all. And in this Light of Life, and newneſs of Nature in Chriſt, runs the Bloud which clenſeth, and not elſwhere. It runs not according to mens notions, but in its own life, virtue &amp; power in the heart: where (where it is livingly felt) the iniquity is waſhed away, the ſin is gone, the everlaſting Righteouſneſs appears, yea the Water-ſprings, which waſheth and keepeth clean continually. Away with your Notions and empty husks, O ſeveral ſorts of Profeſſors, come to the thing it ſelf, or rather wait on the Lord to be led to it, that ye may Seed, the Seed, the pure Seed, the living Seed, the Holy One of God, and may know its planting and growth in you, and your uncloathing and emptying of all elſe, that ye may be cloathed upon and filled with it. And in the ſence of it, and unity with it, ye will own and love what comes from it, and rejoyce in all the ſpringings of its Light, either within or without.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:39164:3"/>
            <head>Of the Church-ſtate under the Goſpel.</head>
            <p>THe <hi>Jews</hi> Church-ſtate under the Law was precious, who (walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with God, according to the Covenant of the Law) were an holy People, nigh and dear unto God above all other People. But they provoked him ſo continually and grievouſly, that (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of bleſſings) they drew plagues upon themſelves, and were at laſt by his righteous Judgments made deſolate, and cut off from being any longer his ſelect Nation and People.</p>
            <p>The Church-ſtate of the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> under the Goſpel, is much more precious and glorious, they being gathered into the ſubſtance of that, whereof the <hi>Jews</hi> State had but the ſhadow. The Preſence of God, the manifeſtation of his Life and Power is more inward and bright among them; their union with him more cloſe, their communion and joy more fell, he tabernacling among them, dwelling and walking with them, and advancing them into the ſtate of ſons and daughters, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Law-ſtate was but a ſtate of ſervitude. And their ſtanding alſo is more firm; the Covenant wherein they ſtand, being more able to hold them together with God than the other was. The ſtanding of the other was by the works of the Law, which they were to obſerve and live. The ſtanding of theſe is in the Faith, which is from the Power, which worketh their works in them and for them.</p>
            <p>Yet, as they are gathered in the Faith: ſo their ſtanding is in the Faith; and out of it they cannot be preſerved. So that (before they are eſtabliſhed) there is a poſſibility of their fal from the Faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their ſtanding is, and from the Power which preſerveth. And if they ſo fall, they are liable to be cut off, as the <hi>Jews</hi> were, as their Apoſtle tels them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20, 21, 22. In the fear, in the humility before the Lord, in keeping to the Faith their ſafety is: but if they become high-minded, becauſe of their State and Church-priviledges; if they think their ſtanding ſo ſure, as that they are out of the danger of falling: then they are out of the fear, out of the humility, out of the Faith which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves; and being out of the Preſervation, they muſt needs fall, and ſo continuing muſt needs be cut off.</p>
            <p>Now the ſame Apoſtle doth not only warn them to take heed of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from the Faith, but afterwards expreſly foretels of a falling away, even that there muſt come ſuch a thing among them alſo; yea, and of
<pb facs="tcp:39164:4"/>
ſuch a falling away from the Truth and Power of Life, as ſhould give Antichriſt advantage to get into God's Temple, and ſit there as God, taking upon him the power and authority, as if he had the true Power and Authority of God, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 4. And what doth he then? doth he not corrupt all? even as God's Power and Preſence purifies and preſerves all. And as he ſhews himſelf as God: ſo doth he not alſo ſhew forth his Church, as God's Church? Yes, it goes ſo in the World, as God's. All that drink of his Spouſes Cup take it to be ſo, who are very many and great ones, even Kings and Inhabiters of the Earth, Peoples, Multitudes, Nations and Tongues (<hi>Rev.</hi> 17.2, 15. &amp; chap. 18.3.) and none are able to diſcern that it is not ſo, but thoſe that are anointed with the true eye-ſalve, which giveth to ſee through his deceits, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.20. For he cometh <hi>with all deceivableneſs of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs</hi> (2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9, 10.) he makes the Church (after he hath got poſſeſſion of it and made it his, ſitting as God in it) appear as like the true Church as poſſibly he can, that he may hold up his myſtery of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit in the World, which if once diſcerned, would ſoon fall and come to nothing; 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5.</p>
            <p>To open theſe things a little more fully and further from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that they who yet cannot read otherwiſe, may read them there, and come in ſome meaſure to the acknowledgment of the Truth, and wait for the Power from on high, from whence is the true Faith (wherin is the true Church, and its ſtanding) for want of which the World is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Wilderneſs; full indeed of Profeſſion, but very empty of the nature and life of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>Chriſt tels his Diſciples, that falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſhould come and deceive many; yea that they ſhould prevail ſo far, as if it were poſſible, to deceive the very Elect, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.15 &amp; ch. 24.11, 24. The Lord God had ſent forth his truth, and now after it he ſuffers to go forth a power of Deceit, a mighty power, even having all maner of Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vableneſs of unrighteouſneſs in it, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.9, 10, 11. And it works according to its power, it gathers all its own every where. Not one, but he that is of the Elect Seed can ſtand before it. Now the reaſon, why God ſuffered this to go forth, was in Judgment. Men had dallied with the Truth, had took up a Form of Godlineſs, and rejected the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: therfore God withdraws from the Form, and ſuffers the unclean ſpirit to enter it, and the uncircumciſed nature of man to ſhelter it ſelf there. It aroſe alſo from the Devil's ſubtilty, who finding himſelf diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſing of his Kingdom, played this Maſterpiece (both to ſave what he could at preſent, and to recover the reſt again in proceſs of time) He (in his Apoſtles and Miniſters) takes upon him the profeſſion of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39164:4"/>
               <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> ſending them forth as the Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13, 15.) but for all that, they were ſtill of the worldly na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of the worldly root, ſpirit and principle: And ſo by them, he brings forth <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> (or the profeſſion and obſervation of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion) in ſuch a way, as would pleaſe the worldly mind and nature: And bringing it forth ſo, he gathers to him all, that were not gathered and preſerved by the Power, and ſo becomes the greater Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Church in view, and the reſt (as to the outwardneſs of their Church-ſtate) are fain to give way, and retire into the Power, cut of their former place and ſtation in the world, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>Now as Chriſt had ſaid, that falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets ſhould come: ſo <hi>John</hi> ſaid they were come, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.18. and alſo ſhewed from whence they come, <hi>They went out from us,</hi> ver. 19. They were ſuch as came into the Form among us, but were not begotten of the Life, nor ſubject to the Power with us. And there were many of them, <hi>chap.</hi> 4.1. and ſuch they were as had a great power of Deceit, and came therewith to ſeduce them, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.26. Therefore he bids them (in the Unction which they had received, <hi>v.</hi> 27. which ſearcheth and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth all) <hi>try the ſpirits.</hi> If their ſpirit (or the ſpirit that is in them) confeſs Chriſt (who is the power of the endleſs life, the ſum, ſubſtance and end of all that which ſhadowed-forth life) they are of God, <hi>chap.</hi> 4.2. But if their ſpirit confeſs not Chriſt come in the fleſh, though they may ſeem never ſo much to preach him, they are not of God, <hi>v.</hi> 3. Now whoſe ſpirit confeſſeth Chriſt? Surely his only that is ſubject to him. He that preacheth Chriſt in words, and denieth him in works, (whoſe works are not wrought in Chriſt, nor brought forth by Chriſt) his confeſſion is but outward, but formal; it is no true confeſſion. It is but the confeſſion of his mouth, not of his ſpirit: and he is, in the ſight of God, not a confeſſor, but a denier of him. And who ſo is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled by God to try ſpirits (and waiteth in his Light and Anointing to try ſuch) findeth him to be ſo, notwithſtanding all his fair words and ſpeeches of Chriſt, and his pretending to be his Miniſter, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2. For men with fine words and fair ſpeeches may deceive the hearts of the ſimple: but they cannot deceive thoſe, to whom God giveth abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to try ſpirits. Could the Devil deceive <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>Thou art the Son of God?</hi> No, <hi>Chriſt</hi> knew his ſpirit to be againſt him, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thoſe words. And can the miniſters of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> deceive the Elect of God, when they preach up <hi>Chriſt</hi> (in words) to be the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and Redeemer, and yet own not that Life and Power which ſaves, but perſecute it wherever they find it? No, The ſame Spirit of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in them diſcerneth quite through their words, to their ſpirit.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39164:5"/>
               <hi>My Sheep,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>hear my voice,</hi> Joh. 10.27. Man may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and caught in the ſnare: but the Elect, the Sheep know the voice of the Shepherd from the voice of the Stranger. If the Stranger ſay, <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the Son of God: though he believes and owns the thing, yet they receive it not from his mouth. Well; whence are theſe falſe Prophets and falſe Chriſts? <hi>They are of the World.</hi> That's their root. Thence they come. They are of the worldly ſpirit, the worldly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the worldly nature, only cloathed outwardly with a profeſſion and ſhew of the Doctrine and Practices of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> And what do they do? <hi>They preach worldly things.</hi> They ſuit their doctrine to the worldly nature, principle and ſpirit. And what is their ſucceſs? <hi>The World heareth them,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.5. The earthly wiſdom in man falls in with them, judges them to be right, owns them, ſets up their way of Chriſtianity and Worſhip in the World: and thus the World become <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Thoſe which came in the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the World could not receive. (<hi>He that knoweth God, heareth us;</hi> not the World, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.6.) There were but a few (in compariſon) gathered here and there then: a few in one place, a few in another. The Doctrine that comes forth in the Power, ſcatters the worldly part. Man's wiſdom, man's nature cannot receive it, in the Love and Life of it. But when theſe falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets come, the World can turn <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> then a whole City, or a whole Nation can preſently become a Church. Why ſo? Theſe come in that, which the World can receive, which their wiſdom can anſwer, fall in with, and ſubject to. Theſe can bring forth a Croſs, which the World can like, fall down and worſhip; but the Croſs of <hi>Christ</hi> they cannot: for that crucifies and ſlayes the worldly nature, wherever it is felt, taken up, and ſubjected to. The way of Life is ſtrait and narrow, and few there be that can walk therein: but a broader way more may walk in. The true Church is not eaſily found or entred into; but the falſe is wider and far larger, yea, deſirable to the fleſh. The true Church is circumſpect, will admit none but in the way of God's Wiſdom and Power; but the falſe Church proſtitutes and thruſts her ſelf upon all. She meets men in the ſtreets and forceth them into her bed; whereas the voice of the true Church is, Wait for the preparation, for the being changed by that which giveth entrance into the Truth: for the Builder of the Church is God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.4. (he builds this Houſe by Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. as by <hi>Moſes</hi> he built the Houſe under the Law) and he is the adder to the Building, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.47.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Paul</hi> alſo, writing to <hi>Timothy,</hi> tells him of perilous times in the laſt dayes, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. For when the laſt dayes come, and the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts and falſe Prophets appear, then men are in great danger of being
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39164:5"/>
deceived, and of making ſhipwrack of Faith and a good Conſcience. Then he that is not in the Truth, but only in the form and outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, will be ſwallowed up by the deceit, and take up his dwelling in the Form with out the Power: for ſo ſaith the Apoſtle concerning them, v. 5. they have a Form of Godlineſs, but deny the Power of it. And all manner of Wickedneſs will ſhelter it ſelf under this Form. <hi>Self-love, Covetouſneſs, Boaſtings, Pride, Blaſphemy, Diſobedience to Parents, Unthankfulneſs, Unholineſs, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 2, 3, 4. and indeed what not? For what is ſo evil, which cannot ſhelter it ſelf under that Form of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Profeſſion, where there is not the true Power and Life of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to reſiſt and ſubdue it?</p>
            <p>Now mark; When theſe Antichriſts and falſe Prophets had got up into a body and ſtrength, gaining Authority and Credit in the World; what did they then do, but endeavour wholly to cruſh and ſuppreſs the Truth, with thoſe that abode ſtill in it? Then the Dragon, with his Angels, fighteth with <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angels. They had ſtill been fighting with the Apoſtles and Miniſters of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> endeavouring to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parage them, and eat out their eſteem in the Churches (as 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.) but they could not prevail; Satan, in all his enterprizes, fell down like Lightning, before the Glory and Power of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Apoſtles and Miniſters. But when the Apoſtacy encreaſed, and the Churches pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked their Preſerver, growing cold in Love, and faint in Faith (being lifted up with their Gifts, thinking highly of themſelves, and their ſtanding to be firm) and many received not the love of the Truth, but only a profeſſion of it for by-ends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then the Lord began to threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſome with the removal of their Candleſtick, and did afterwards proceed in Judgment, even to let the falſe Prophets and Antichriſts prevail, and ſtrong Deluſions enter, that they who had dallied with the Truth, might be fruſtrated of the Salvation they expected by it, meeting with a Lie (which deſtroyeth) in the ſtead of it, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12. And ſo God, who before built up, in his jealouſie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation afterwards threw down (men abiding not in the Faith, nor in the Power, but in the Form and outward Profeſſion, which, ſeparated from the Power, the Lord abhorreth.) What he loved, he ſecured for himſelf, (his holy Temple, his holy Altar, his ſpiritual Worſhippers:) and what he regarded not (which was the Form and outward Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, now polluted) he gave to the heatheniſhly-profeſſing ſpirit; and there they worſhip, and magnifie their own ſtate, prizing it by its out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward glory and appearance, and not by a right ſence and knowledge of it in the Truth. Read theſe things outwardly, in the letter (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wait upon God that ye may read them, who cauſed them to be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39164:6"/>
writ to that end, for to be read and underſtood) <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. &amp; <hi>chap.</hi> 11. 1, 2. where the battel of the Dragon is related, and God's taking down his Building, and diſpoſing of it according to his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Again, mark. Antichriſt gets into the Temple (upon the falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way) ſits there as God, ruling, giving Laws, and exacting Obedience in the Name of God. But <hi>when was this to be?</hi> In the laſt times, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. (which would be very perilous, through the power of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs and deceit, then getting up.) <hi>When did thoſe times begin?</hi> They began in the Apoſtles dayes. The Myſtery of Iniquity was then at work, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.7. Yea, ſaith <hi>John, it is the laſt time;</hi> by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Antichriſts and Deceivers we know it to be ſo, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Christ</hi> ſaid, They ſhould come; <hi>John</hi> ſaid, they are come; <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw them then at work in the myſterious Power of Darkneſs. But they could not carry their work through; the Spirit and Power of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Apoſtles ſtood ſo much in their way: but after they were removed out of the way, Antichriſt got up his Myſtery of Deceit apace. Well, <hi>how long doth he reign?</hi> Even till the very coming of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Power; yea, there is ſome remainder of him, till the very brightneſs of his coming, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. This Myſtery of Iniquity hath power and authority over all the wiſdom of man: but the appearance of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the Spirits of his People, hath power over it, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth it, by opening its nakedneſs and cauſing its darkneſs to appear; and the brightneſs of his coming ſhall quite diſſolve and ſcatter it: For it is but a miſt of darkneſs, it hath no being in the Truth, nor can it ſtand before the Truth. So <hi>Babylon</hi> is found ſtanding at the very laſt; juſt before the breaking forth and coming down of the new Jeruſalem and the Marriage of the Lamb with his Bride, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.6, 7. <hi>What is Babylon?</hi> A Myſtery of Iniquity in a Form of Godlineſs. A Profeſſion, a People, a Religion, that ſeem to ſet up Chriſt; but ſet up another nature, ſpirit and power in his ſtead. A Church that is not of God, not formed in his Divine Wiſdom, not brought forth in his Light and Power, and in the ſeaſon of his Will; but of man, and by man, that can go no further in Religion than the number of a man. <hi>Sion,</hi> under the Goſpel, is not literal, but myſtical: and ſo is <hi>Babylon</hi> alſo, who is the mother of Fornications, who teacheth her daughters to adulterate from the Life and from the Power, who never knew the Marriage of the Lamb in his Spirit, nor his pure Bed of Life, but enter into the cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and bed of a ſtrange ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>But what is the ſtate of the Church all this while, from this hour of corruption, till the coming of Chriſt in his Spirit and Power?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A ſtate of deſolation, a ſtate of widowhood, a wilderneſs-ſtate,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39164:6"/>
where her living body is not diſcerned by the vultrous eye; but her children, whenever they appear witneſſing for her, are perſecuted, hunted, afflicted, and ſometimes ſlain. This bloody Church, which comes from the red Dragon, and rules in his ſpirit and nature, drinks the blood of the Lambs and Martyrs of <hi>JESUS,</hi> who in their ſeveral Ages are his faithful Witneſſes, and love not their lives unto the death. And here the Truth, and that which hath appeared of the true Church in the world, for Ages and Generations (ever ſince this might of the Dragon's and Antichriſts darkneſs, and his ſitting in the Temple un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an appearance of light) hath only been to be found, even among the Perſecuted Ones, who have been dear to God, of whom the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing World hath not been worthy, no not at all, of that heavenly life, ſpirit and power, which dwelt in them, and through which they have been able to teſtifie for the Truth, and bear up their heads againſt the malice and perſecutions of their enemies, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.11, 17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>chap.</hi> 11.3, 7. <hi>chap.</hi> 13.15, 16, 17. <hi>chap.</hi> 14.12. <hi>chap.</hi> 17.6.</p>
            <p>Now, for a cloſe, There are a few Queſtions in my heart, briefly to propound and anſwer, which it may pleaſe God to reach forth to his Witneſs in ſuch, who in diſtruſt of themſelves and their own wiſdom, ſhall wait upon him for underſtanding. The Queſtions are theſe. Firſt, what a true Church is? 2dly, How a True Church may be known? 3. How a True Church may continue ſo? 4. How a Church may loſe its ſtate and being? 5. When a Church hath loſt its ſtate and being?</p>
            <p>Queſt. 1. <hi>What a true Church is?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A true Church is a truly Spiritual Body, gathered out of the World, or worldly nature and ſpirit, into God's Spirit and Nature, there to live and walk with him, and worſhip him in Spirit and Truth, and for him to tabernacle in and walk among, and fill with his glorious Preſence and powerful Life, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.21, 22. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.23. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. It is not the Profeſſion of the Truth, makes a true Believer; nor is it a company of Profeſſors makes a true Church: but their proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from, and union with the Truth it ſelf, and their abiding in the Life and Power of that which they profeſs; <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.16.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>How a true Church may be known?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There muſt be ſomewhat in man to know them, and ſomewhat in them to be known by. That in man which knows them, muſt be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of God in him: for that which is of man cannot meaſure or judg of the things of God. As the worldly wiſdom &amp; ſpirit could not know Chriſt formerly: ſo neither now can it know his Church. Many may appear to be Churches of Chriſt, and yet not be ſo: and that which is ſo, may not appear ſo. In this caſe, who ſhall diſtinguiſh? Not he that judgeth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39164:7"/>
according to the appearance, but he that judgeth the Righteous Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therefore it is not for every man to take upon him to judge, which is the true Church: but firſt to wait upon God to be led into that, and in ſome meaſure born of that, which giveth ability to judge. <hi>Wiſdom is juſtified of her Children:</hi> but of others ſhe is condemned for fooliſhneſs, and the fooliſhneſs juſtified in her ſtead.</p>
            <p>And there is alſo ſomewhat for the Church to be known by, which is that which diſtinguiſheth her from all other Aſſemblies and Gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, which is the nature, life and preſence of the Head with her and in her. This none hath, but the true Church, the gathered Body, the ſeparate Body of the Lamb, which is of his fleſh and of his bones, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.29, 30. Her Husband is with her, his life is in her: for ſhe is a living body, or gathering of living ſtones. So that find the true life of the Lamb any where, there is ſomewhat of his Church: find a ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering in his Life, Name and Power, there is his Church, and he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: <hi>for where two or three are gathered together in my Name, there am I in the midst of them,</hi> Mat. 18.20.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>How a true Church may continue ſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By abiding in the Spirit, Life, and Power, that gathered and built them up into a Church. This firſt gave them their being; and this ſtill preſerves them in their being: (if they abide till they be perfected and eſtabliſhed) but falling or being cut off from this, they wither, die, and come to nothing. Even as a Diſciple, departing out of the Vine, making ſhipwrack of the Faith, loſeth that which made him a Diſciple or Chriſtian, <hi>John</hi> 15.6. So a Church, departing from the Spirit and Life of what they profeſs, languiſh by degrees, even till their life be wholly extinct, and they wholly loſe that ſtate and being which they had by their gathering. Thus the Churches in <hi>Aſia,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to corrupt, grew formal, lukewarm, dead, &amp;c. were warned to repent and ſtrenthen that which remained, leſt they were ſpued out, the Candleſtick removed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Rev. 2d &amp; 3d chapters.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>How may a Church loſe its ſtate and being?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Several wayes; as firſt, By departing from the Truth and Simplicity of the Goſpel, letting in Doctrines, Principles, Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Cuſtoms and Practices, which are not of the pure Spirit, nor in the unity of it, but from the corrupt ſpirit, and which corrupt the minds of them that are entangled in them. Corrupt doctrines, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt principles, corrupt practices, &amp;c. they all have of the nature and poiſon of death in them; and as they prevail, they bring death upon (and engage God againſt) that Perſon or Church where they get do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. See what danger one corrupt doctrine of the <hi>Nicholaitans</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:39164:7"/>
brought the Church of <hi>Pergamus</hi> unto, even of God's coming forth with his ſword and fighting againſt her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.16. And if God, who is the Defender of his Church, Himſelf fight againſt her, how ſhall ſhe ſtand?</p>
            <p n="2">2. By negligence and ſluggiſhneſs in the Truth: by this means alſo life may languiſh and extinguiſh by degrees, even till death come wholly over and ſwallow it up, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. If the firſt Love do but abate and wax cold, Iniquity will be abounding, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.12. and the Church will be in danger of loſing its Candleſtick, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.4, 5.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By God's withdrawing his Preſence and Power, (for theſe or ſuch cauſes aboveſaid) which nouriſheth and preſerveth. For the life of a Church (as well as of a Diſciple) is fed and nouriſhed from the Fountain or Vine; and if it miſs of the nouriſhment, its life cannot long continue. The <hi>Jews</hi> may keep up their Sacrifices, and reading of the Law: but yet they are a dead people to God, after their cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off from the Olive-tree. And the Gentiles may worſhip in the outward Court, and keep up the outward Ordinances, after God's rejecting and cutting them off alſo, and be as dead to God therein, as the <hi>Jews</hi> in theirs, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1, 2. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.21, 22.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By their liſtning and yeelding to the power of the Enemy, who quickly deceiveth, (with his Lies, inſtead of the Truth) deſtroyeth, and layeth waſte ſuch buildings, where God in his juſt Judgement letteth him forth upon them. For the Gates of Hell will prevail againſt that building, which the Arm of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not ſtretched forth (or ceaſeth) to defend. And as the defence of every particular Building upon the Rock, is in its abiding there, and ſubjecting to the Head; ſo the defence of larger Gatherings, or Churches, is no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. As their union and gathering is; ſo is their ſtanding, to wit, in believing and giving up to their Leader, hearkning to his voice, and obeying him only. But if they hearken to a Stranger, if they hear another voice than his; if they follow another ſpirit, letting in his lies and deceit; they cannot keep their ſtanding in the Truth, but in ſo doing depart from it, and loſe the promiſe and protection of it. For, as before, by God's gathering them from the ſpirit of darkneſs, they became His, and met with his Power, Preſence and Bleſſing: ſo afterwards, being again (by any ſubtilty of deceit) gathered from the Truth it ſelf, into ſome likeneſs and appearance of it, which the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my hath formed, they become the Enemies Synagogue, not God's Church, into which he entereth again, and dwelleth there, in that likeneſs and appearance. And this Houſe, which was once cleanſed,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39164:8"/>
ſwept and garniſhed by God, being again recovered and repoſſeſſed by the Enemy, becomes worſe and more filthy in the nature of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, than it was before. What is more pure, glorious and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, than a true Church of God, which is ſanctified by his Spirit, and holds forth the vertues and pure nature of his Life in the world? what is more filthy and abominable, and where doth <hi>Satan</hi> more ſtrongly dwell and act, than in that which pretends to be a Church and is not? The Promiſes of God are only to the Seed abſolutely; but not ſo to any man or ſociety of men, but as (in the tender mercy of the Lord) they are gathered into, and preſerved in the Seed, in the way that the Lord hath choſen and appointed. For the way of Life is glorious and perfect, and the Lord will honour it; ſo that thoſe that expect to reap Salvation from Him, muſt walk and abide with Him therein: for beſides Him there is no Saviour; and beſides his Way, there is no way of Salvation, either for any man or Church.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>When hath a Church lost its ſtate and being?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> When its nature is changed, when it is overcome by and gathered into another power and ſpirit, than it was firſt gathered into by the Lord; when its ſtanding is not in the Spirit, nor after the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but in the fleſh and after the fleſh; when its wayes are carnal, its weapons carnal; when its hedge or wall is broken down, and the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the world not kept out, but entred into it and become one with it. Then it is no longer of God, and ſeparate from the world, but one in nature, ſtate and being with the world. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p>Theſe things are written in the love and good-will of God, that men may ſee that ſpirit, which hath bewitched and entangled them from him, with the wayes and falſe appearances wherein it hath entangled them, and may wait on the Lord (in truth of heart) for his Light, Guidance and Power to deliver them; that ſo they may come into his Holy Land, and within the limits of his Holy City, out of all pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted Lands and Buildings (where his Holy Nature dwelleth not, and the Pure Dominion of his Holy Life and Power is not felt) that they may ſing Praiſe to Him among his Redeemed Ones, for his precious Redemption; who is breaking the bonds of Captivity, and redeeming His out of all Lands and Countries, wherein they have been ſcattered in the cloudy and dark day, Glory in the Higheſt to his Name for evermore.</p>
            <div type="queries">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:39164:8"/>
               <head>Some <hi>Queries</hi> to the Profeſſours of Chriſtianity, to provoke them to jealouſie for their good.</head>
               <p>Qu. 1. <hi>Have ye eat of the Bread and drank of the Wine in the Father's Kingdom, which they that have received the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and are in the Kingdom, eat and drink of?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. 2. <hi>Have ye known the heavenly</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and are ye come to it, as the Chriſtians were in the Apoſtles dayes?</hi> Hebr. 12.22.</p>
               <p>Qu. 3. <hi>Are ye in Him that is true, and your Churches and Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therings in God, and in the Name of his Son? Is your being and dwelling in the Eternal Life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. 4. <hi>Have ye received the Promiſe of the Father, even the excellent Spirit of the Son?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. 5. <hi>Have ye the true Faith? Do the living Waters ſpring out of your bowels, according as the Scriptures have ſaid?</hi> He that believeth on me, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.38. &amp; <hi>ch.</hi> 4.14.</p>
               <p>Qu. 6. <hi>Doth God tabernacle in you? is his dwelling among you? doth he walk up and down in your ſpirits, and ſup with you, and you with him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. 7. <hi>Are ye in the New Covenant; taught of God ſo, as ye need no man to teach you? and your ſins ſo blotted out (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Covenant) as to hinder no good things from you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things were ſpoken of in the Law and Prophets, to be fulfilled, witneſſed and enjoyed under the Power and Life of the Goſpel; which is not a ſtate of the names and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellings of things, as under the Law, but of the preſence and enjoyment of the things themſelves: and ſo far as ye fall ſhort of them, ye fall ſhort of the ſtate of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="observations">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:39164:9"/>
            <head>SOME OBSERVATIONS UPON THE Eternal Judgement, As it is expreſſed by CHRIST, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.31. to the end of the Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerve</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>THe condition of Chriſt here in this world, in many of his Members, in their ſeveral Ages and Generations. He is <hi>hungry, thirſty, a ſtranger, naked, ſick and in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:</hi> yea indeed, what is there of miſery, ſhame and reproach, which he is not expoſed to, or which they are not expoſed to, who entertain Him as their Lord and King, and are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in their obedience and ſubjection to him? <hi>ver.</hi> 35, 36, &amp; 43.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>The notice Chriſt takes of what is done in this kind, or not done in this kind, to any of his ſuffering Members, which extends to all, even the very leaſt. <hi>Inſomuch as ye have done it unto one of the leaſt of theſe, ye have done it unto me,</hi> ver. 40. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as ye did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, ye did it not to me,</hi> ver. 45.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>The honourable eſteem Chriſt hath of his poor ſuffering Members, with what eye of contempt ſoever the World looks upon them, yet he looks upon them as his Brethren, <hi>ver.</hi> 40.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39164:9"/>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>The different carriages of perſons towards Chriſt, in this his low condition in his Members. Some gave him meat, ſome gave him drink, ſome took him in, ſome cloathed him, ſome viſited and came unto him; <hi>ver.</hi> 35, 36. Others did none of theſe things unto him, <hi>ver.</hi> 43.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>The different Judgment Chriſt paſſeth upon theſe, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their different carriages. The one he pronounceth <hi>bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of his Father,</hi> judging them to the inheritance of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Eternal Life, <hi>ver.</hi> 34, &amp; 46. The other he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth <hi>Curſed,</hi> and adjudgeth to Everlaſting Puniſhment in the fire of his Wrath, <hi>ver.</hi> 41 &amp; 46.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>The ground or reaſon why thoſe, who did not miniſter to him, neglected him, which was their ignorance of him. They ſaw indeed, and knew ſeveral perſons to be in ſuch kind of conditions, but they did not know that it was Chriſt which ſuffered in them: This is implied in their Anſwer to him, <hi>ver.</hi> 44. <hi>When ſaw we thee an hungry, or athirſt, or a ſtranger, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, or ſick, or in priſon, and did not miniſter unto thee?</hi> v. 45.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſer.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>That it will not excuſe men from the Judgment, their not knowing of Chriſt in his Members: but if they neglect and have not done this thing (though they may plead never ſo ſtrongly that they did not know any ſuch) they will in our and muſt ſuffer the Judgment. The <hi>Jews</hi> cryed up <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, which had been before, and yet perſecuted Chriſt and his Apoſtles: And many now cry up the Prophets, and Chriſt's appearance in a body of fleſh (with his Death, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, Aſcenſion, &amp;c.) and alſo the Apoſtles, both their words &amp; practices; and yet perſecute him (and the ſame pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices) in his preſent Servants and Members. How will theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:39164:10"/>Object.</p>
            <p>But th e that did miniſter unto him, they knew not that it was he neither, as <hi>ver. 37, 38, 39.</hi> Therefore they doing of it igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly (as we may ſay) it ſeemeth to want its due weight, and not to render them ſo worthy of the reward, as if they had done it in a clear and diſtinct underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Anſwer.</p>
            <p>They did not know it ſo, as to put ſo great a value upon it, as Chriſt here doth: but they knew that they had done things of this kind, and that they had done them on Chriſt's account. But that Chriſt was ſo in thoſe to whom they did them, as he now ſpeaks; and that he would ſet ſo high an eſteem of it, that they were not aware of. Was it thou thy ſelf that waſt naked, ſick, in priſon, &amp;c.? and didſt thou take all this as done to thee? This is wonderful to us, that thou ſhouldſt ſo ſet by what we poor worms did to thy ſuffering Saints, in thy Name and Fear.</p>
            <p>Queſt.</p>
            <p>But why doth Chriſt make this the ground of the General and Univerſal Judgment? Men have committed many other ſins (ſome of which are in appearance far greater:) why doth Chriſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion none of them, but fix the Judgment only upon this?</p>
            <p>Anſw.</p>
            <p>Surely becauſe this is more in his eye, and more hateful to him than them all. This argues an evil nature and ſpirit, and the joyning of the mind to the wicked one, more than them all. For it plainly ſhews, that there is none of the Love and Nature of Chriſt in ſuch perſons: for if there be of the Love and Nature of Chriſt in any perſon, it will encline his heart towards thoſe which are Chriſt's, and eſpecially in their ſuffering conditions. He therefore that hath no ſence of thoſe that belong to Chriſt, in their ſuffering conditions, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth plainly, that he hath none of Chriſt's Nature in him, and ſo is not at all found in that which Chriſt comes to ſave, but in that which he comes to judge and deſtroy for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:39164:10"/>Now I have three Queſtions more to propoſe, which I deſire that all men that read, may judge of it in that, which giveth the true ſenſe and judgment of their weight.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If this be the cauſe and ground of the Eternal Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whether it may not alſo be the ground of Temporal Judgments on Perſon; and Nations, to wit, if there be ſuch a thing to be found in them, as neglecting to miniſter to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his ſuffering Members?</p>
            <p n="2">2. If there be not only this to be found, but alſo a cauſing of him in his Members thus to ſuffer (a cauſing of their hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, thurſt, nakedneſs, ſickneſs, impriſonment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) whether this is not of very great force to draw down Plagues, Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Miſeries upon a Nation?</p>
            <p n="3">3. If there have been ſuch ſins committed, God's Anger provoked, and his Judgments drawn down, whether it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to ſtop them, or there can be any reaſonable hope of the diverting of them, without a deep humbling before God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the thing in the ſight of the World (as it hath been done in the ſight of the World) and laying ſuch a foundation for the future, as the Lord and men may be ſatisfied and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that no ſuch thing ſhall be done any more? Was it not a ſhameful thing, that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the outwardly holy City (and chief, if not only profeſſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of the world) ſhould ſtone, caſt out, perſecute, put to death, &amp;c. the Prophets and Chriſt of God, and ſet up Prieſts and Prophets of their own? And where and by whom are the Witneſſes and Martyrs hunted and ſlain? Is is not ſtill in that which is called the <hi>Chriſtian World?</hi> do not they ſtrive (each ſort) for their Forms, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the Life and Power, and thoſe which follow the Lamb therein, out of their Forms, from which his Life and Spirit cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and gathereth? O that the World were awaked, O that this Nation were awakened! Have there not been Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments enow to awaken it! O do not dally: ye have God to deal with, who hath brought his Truth and People upon the Stage; who is ariſen againſt the Darkneſs (which hath
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39164:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
long poſſeſſed the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and held his People in capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity under their corrupt wills and wiſdom) and to bind down ſin and iniquity in men. O do not ſay, <hi>Let us break their bonds in ſunder, and caſt away their cords from us;</hi> but rather let every one be willing to be bound by the pure Light of God, by that which is holy of God in him (from the King that ſits upon the Throne, even to the very Beggar on the dunghil) that ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity may be purged out of the hearts of men, and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, not a vainly-profeſſing Nation, but indeed an Holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Lord; that Peace and Righteouſneſs, Love and Mercy, yea ſweet and tender Bowels may dwell within it, and flow up and down in all its borders; to the glory of God's Truth, which is able to work this (were it but let in, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and ſubjected to in the minds of men) and to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and joy of the hearts of all in the Nation.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Writt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <date>29th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>By <hi>Iſaac Penington</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
